Guide to the Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival Records, 1980-1994 CTC.1994.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival Records
Bulk, 1987-1994
1980-1994
CTC.1994.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
The Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival is an annually held educational and cultural complement to the Pittsburgh Lesbian and Gay Film Society’s year round program meant to foster appreciation and visibility through film media. The Festival hosts members of the film industry from Pittsburgh, Ohio, and West Virginia; it aims to educate, enlighten, and entertain audiences while increasing unity, community, and pride among lesbians and gay men of the tri-state region. The collection primarily comprises budgeting and programming plans, Festival bylaws, grant applications, press coverage, and information on other gay and lesbian film festivals in the United States between 1980 and 1992.
Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival Records, 1983-1994, CTC.1994.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
The Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival (PILGFS) collection is composed of bill receipts, programming information, public and private grant applications, and information on other gay and lesbian film festivals in the United States between 1988 and 1994. The first series comprises budgeting plans, Festival bylaws, billing invoices and receipts, programming information, public and private grant applications, as well as correspondence between Richard Cummings and festival personnel. Included in this series are detailed reports on the Festival’s application and receipt of funding and grants from the Chicago Resource Center, the Lambda Foundation, and the Pennsylvania Council on the Arts. Media coverage on the Festival is included from several local Pittsburgh publications. Finally, the Film Festival’s grant application and lawsuit with the National Alliance for Media Arts and Culture in 1993 are present. The second series includes programs and press coverage on other gay and lesbian film festivals collected by the PILGFS. These materials often make mention of the Film Festival in Pittsburgh, as well as served as tools for planning in the early years of the PILGFS.
History
The Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival (PILGFF) began in 1982 as the Lesbian and Gay Film Series, a project of the Pittsburgh’s Lesbian and Gay Community Center, with the goal of providing opportunities for viewing media by and about lesbian and gay people and their experiences. In partnership with the University of Pittsburgh’s Gay and Lesbian Alliance, the Film Series was stationed in Oakland. In 1985 the Film Series moved off-campus and became a separate event, formed its own Board of Directors, and launched the first film festival in 1986 with the cooperation of Pittsburgh Filmmakers.
In 1987, with Richard Cummings as Executive Director, the Film Festival incorporated, was granted non-profit status, and applied for funding as a major presenter of lesbian and gay media in Pennsylvania and the nation. The annual Film Festival has grown to a ten-day program each October presenting over fifty films and videos in a number of venues, as well as producing, hosting, and participating in a wide array of cultural and community events throughout the year. Originally only hosting audiences at the Pittsburgh Filmmakers’ Oakland Screening Room and Fulton Theatre, the Film Festival has expanded into a multi-venue event and presents at several theatres, including Pittsburgh’s Byham and South Side Works theatres. With an increase in programming and attendance, the Film Festival has continued to augment funding and media coverage, receiving grants from the Chicago resource Center, the Pennsylvania Council on the Arts, and the Lambda Foundation.
The Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival highlights major feature films of interest to the lesbian and gay community, as well as provides a venue for independent film and video from the United States and abroad. The Film Festival also sponsors an educational symposium featuring an internationally acclaimed figure in lesbian and gay media. Past speakers have included independent filmmakers Isaac Julien, Peggy Gilpin, Cheryl Dunye, Rob Marshall, and art critic and AIDS activist Douglas Crimp.
In 2006, the organization changed its corporate name to the Pittsburgh Lesbian and Gay Film Society in order to show its dedicated commitment to become an organization that provides year round activities. The Pittsburgh Lesbian and Gay Film Society is now the presenter of the Annual Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival.
Gay & Lesbian Community Center of Pittsburgh (Pa.).; Pittsburgh International Lesbian and Gay Film Festival.; Clippings (Information artifacts); Film festivals -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Gay and lesbian film festivals -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Gay and lesbian film festivals -- United States; Gay culture -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Gays -- Social life and customs; Gays in motion pictures; Grant proposals; Grants; Homosexuality in motion pictures; Lesbians -- Social life and customs; Lesbians in motion pictures; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Popular culture; Programs (Documents); Theater; Theater programs
- Office files, 1984-1994; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The first series comprises budgeting plans, Festival bylaws, billing invoices and receipts, programming information, public and private grant applications, as well as correspondence between Richard Cummings and festival personnel. Included in this series are detailed reports on the Festival’s application and receipt of funding and grants from the Chicago Resource Center, the Lambda Foundation, and the Pennsylvania Council on the Arts. Media coverage on the Festival is included from several local publications, including Pittsburgh’s Out Magazine and City Paper. Their grant application and lawsuit with the National Alliance for Media Arts and Culture in 1993 are present. The materials are arranged in chronological order by festival year.
  - Pittsburgh Gay & Lesbian Community Center Film Series, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Film Festival - invoices and correspondence, 1986 (Folder 2)
  - Film Festival - invoices, 1987 (Folder 3)
  - Film Festival - programs, 1987 (Folder 4)
  - Film Festival - press clippings, 1987 (Folder 5)
  - Lambda Foundation -grant, 1987 (Folder 6)
  - Film Festival -bylaws, 1988 (Folder 7)
  - Film Festival - tax information, 1988-1989 (Folder 8)
  - Film Festival -press clippings, 1988 (Folder 9)
  - Film Festival - programs, 1988 (Folder 10)
  - Chicago Resource Center -grant, 1988 (Folder 11)
  - Pennsylvania Council on the Arts - grant, 1988 (Folder 12)
  - Film Festival - invoices, 1989 (Folder 13)
  - Film Festival - press clippings, 1989 (Folder 14)
  - Film Festival -programs, 1989 (Folder 15)
  - Chicago Resource Center - grant, 1989 (Folder 16)
  - Pennsylvania Council on the Arts - grant, 1989 (Folder 17)
  - Film Festival - invoices, 1990 (Folder 18)
  - Film Festival - press clippings, 1990-1991 (Folder 19)
  - Film Festival - programs, 1990 (Folder 20)
  - Chicago Resource Center - grant, 1990 (Folder 21)
  - Lambda Foundation - grant, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Council on the Arts - grant, 1990 (Folder 2)
  - Film Festival - invoices, 1991 (Folder 3)
  - Film Festival - press clippings, 1991 (Folder 4)
  - Film Festival - programs, 1991 (Folder 5)
  - Film Festival - report, 1991 (Folder 6)
  - Chicago Resource Center - grant, 1991 (Folder 7)
  - Pennsylvania Council on the Arts – grant and press clippings, 1991 (Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Humanities Council - grant, 1991 (Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh Foundation - grant, 1991 (Folder 10)
  - Film Festival - invoices, 1991 (Folder 11)
  - Film Festival - press clippings, 1992 (Folder 12)
  - Film Festival - programs, 1992 (Folder 13)
  - Chicago Resource Center - grant, 1992 (Folder 14)
  - National Alliance for Media Arts and Culture - grant, 1991 (Folder 15)
  - Pennsylvania Council on the Arts - grant, 1992 (Folder 16)
  - Film Festival - press clippings, 1993 (Folder 17)
  - Film Festival - programs, 1993 (Folder 18)
  - National Alliance for Media Arts and Culture - grant, 1993 (Folder 19)
  - National Alliance for Media Arts and Culture - lawsuit, 1993 (Folder 20)
  - Pennsylvania Council on the Arts - grant, 1993 (Folder 21)
  - Pittsburgh Foundation - grant, 1993 (Folder 22)
  - Film Festival - press clippings, 1994 (Folder 23)
  - Lambda Foundation - grant, 1994 (Folder 24)
  - National Alliance for Media Arts and Culture - grant, 1994 (Folder 25)
  - Pennsylvania Council for the Arts - grant, 1994 (Folder 26)
- Other Lesbian and Gay film festivals in the United States, 1980-1992; II.
  The second series includes information on other gay and lesbian film festivals collected by the PILGFS. The information collected consists of programs and press coverage. These materials often make mention of the Film Festival in Pittsburgh, as well as served as tools for planning in the early years of the PILGFS.
  - Chicago International Lesbian & Gay Film Festival, 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Los Angeles International Lesbian & Gay Film Festival, 1988-1992 (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous film festivals, 1989 (Folder 3)
  - New York International Festival of Lesbian & Gay Film, 1980-1991 (Folder 4)
  - San Francisco International Lesbian & Gay Film Festival, 1986-1989 (Folder 5)
  - Washington D.C. International Lesbian & Gay Film Festival, 1988 (Folder 6)